{
  "reference_number": "12373",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "I support the most ambitious target of reducing total greenhouse gases to net zero by 2050. I also support taking an evidence-based\n approach to any effort to reduce emissions to have the biggest possible impact. The goal should be to achieve negative (below zero)\n\n levels of long-lived gases (carbon dioxide and nitrous oxide) while significantly reducing short-lived gases (methane) to sustainable\n levels."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "This target should be reached by actually reducing our own emissions or offsetting them by newly planted forests, and not by using\n\n international carbon credits."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I support a capacity to revise the 2050 target, but ONLY in exceptional circumstances. The purpose of the Zero Carbon Act is to\n provide accountability, certainty and flexibility, which it can only do by setting clear and legally-binding emission reduction targets. A\n range of different policy instruments set up to meet the 2050 target will provide flexibility, particularly in response to any changes in\n\n technology e.g. a methane vaccine). Any future revision should require input from the Climate Commission and approval by\n Parliament. I do NOT support revision of the 2050 target for economic reasons."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "Any new government has the flexibility to introduce different policies to meet the upcoming target."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Only under truly exceptional circumstances, such as an extreme natural disaster."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I support the Zero Carbon Act having a strict time frame for setting out policy plans, ideally within months after an emission budget\n\nhas been set."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Any policy plans to meet emission budgets should be comprehensive, fair, cost-effective, environmentally sustainable, and reflect a\ncommitment to Te Tiriti o Waitangi."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I support that the Climate Commission has two main functions: providing expert advice and monitoring progress on achieving the\ntargets."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Expertise in public health (in relation to climate change) is missing from the currently proposed list of expertise."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Adaptation (preparedness for the impacts of climate change, such as droughts, floods, sea level rise, more concurrent hot days with\n\nimpacts on livestock etc) should be part of the Zero Carbon Act."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The government should be required to prepare a national policy plan to address climate risks."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "A Zero Carbon Act must be just and fair and honour Te Tiriti o Waitangi. It has to ensure a fair transition for workers in industry that will\nundergo a downward change and for rural communities whose livelihoods lie in agriculture. The act also needs to avoid passing on\n\nthe costs to future generations."
    }
  ]
}
